Inventory of the Hidayet Dağdeviren collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Hidayet Dağdeviren collection
1797-1955
52000
Hoover Institution Archives
24 manuscript boxes, 10 oversize boxes (13.6 linear feet)
The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, proclamations, speeches, clippings, newspaper issues, maps, posters, and photographs, relating to political and social conditions in Turkey during the Ottoman Empire and the early years of the Turkish Republic, Turkish military activities during World War I, Turkish foreign relations, and ethnic minorities in Turkey.
Dağdeviren, Hidayet
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1952.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Eleanor Bisbee papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Mary Mills Patrick papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Turkish Conference proceedings, Hoover Institution Archives
Turkish subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Vrangel' collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Ahmet Emin Yalman papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
The research materials collected by Hidayet Dağdeviren of Istanbul, Turkey, cover the last years of the Ottoman Empire and the first years of the Republic of Turkey, and in particular documenting social organizations and minorities.
The Ottoman Empire was at the center of interactions between the Eastern and Western worlds for six centuries, and came to an end, as a regime under an imperial monarchy, on November 1, 1922. It formally ended, as a de jure state, on July 24, 1923, under the Treaty of Lausanne.
It was succeeded by the Republic of Turkey, which was officially proclaimed on October 29, 1923.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, proclamations, speeches, clippings, newspaper issues, maps, posters, and photographs, relating to political and social conditions during the last decades of the Ottoman Empire and the early years of the Turkish Republic, Turkish military activities during World War I, Turkish foreign relations, and ethnic minorities in Turkey.
The collection is arranged as originally received from the collector. The following groups of collected research materials were given alphanumeric designations by the collector and have been retained as groups. The Research files contain materials such as correspondence, memoranda, reports, proclamations, speeches, clippings, newspaper issues, maps, posters, and photographs. The Research folios contain materials from the larger group of research files selected by the collector. The Large research dossiers contain oversize materials from the larger group of research files selected by collector. Scrapbooks of newspapers and a group of oversize materials removed from the Research files folders by the Hoover Institution for preservation in oversize files.
Minorities--Turkey.; Turkey--History.; World War, 1914-1918--Turkey.
- Research files, 1797-1943 (Box 1-21)
  Scope and Contents note
  The files include correspondence, memoranda, reports, proclamations, speeches, clippings, newspaper issues, maps, posters, and photographs. Originally designated as "envelopes" by the collector and arranged in an incomplete numerical series of D1-141 and DE1-46. Materials have been rehoused into folders for preservation purposes.
  - Prayer for Success of the Ottoman Army, 26 August 1912 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Reforms regarding Kurdish minorities in Ottoman provinces, draft, circa 1887 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Outline of materials selected from the Dagdeviren collection, circa 1950 (Folder 1: 3)
  - D1. The Kurds and Persia, clippings, 1919-1922 (Folder 1: 4)
  - D2. War of Independence, tracts, clippings, 1919-1923 (Folder 1: 5-9)
  - D6. Mustafa Kemal Atatürk military notes and clippings, 1927 (Folder 1: 10)
  - D8. Sultan Reşad, clippings and pamphlets, 1909 (Folder 1: 11-12)
  - D12. Mustafa Reşid Paşa, Ali Paşa, and Fuad Paşa, clippings and pamphlets, 1912-1942 (Folder 1: 13-15)
  - D13. Albanians, Bosnians, and Turks, clippings, brochures, and maps, 1870-1939 (Folder 2: 1-7)
  - D16. Young Turk Revolution, 1908, clippings, newspapers, posters, and postcards, 1908-1911, 1942 (Folder 2: 8-13)
    See also box 34
  - D17. Turks and Iranians, argument between Zeki Velidi Togan and San'an, clippings from Tasviri Efkâr, 1943 (Folder 3: 1)
  - D18. Hejaz Railway, clippings, notes and posters, 1904 (Folder 3: 2)
  - D19. Greco-Turkish War of 1897, clippings, maps and posters, circa 1897 (Folder 3: 3-6)
  - D21. Circassians, clippings, articles and notes, circa 1938 (Folder 3: 7)
  - D23. Wahhabi order, clippings and pamphlets, circa 1928 (Folder 3: 8)
  - D24. Jewish authors, clippings, 1909-1913 (Folder 3: 9-12)
  - D25. Al-Muntada al-Adabi, literary society (club), Istanbul, 1890-1923
    - Notes and clippings, 1918-1923 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Speeches and letters drafts, 1911-1914 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Letters, circa 1911 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Española-Portugueza-Judaica, Dictionnaire Bibliographique, Strasbourg, 1890 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Club records, circa 1911 (Folder 3: 17)
  - D28. Russo-Turkish War, clippings, maps, and printed matter, 1810-1938 (Folder 4: 1-5)
  - D31. Bosnia-Herzegovina, newspapers, clippings, printed matter, postcards, and maps, 1877-1918 (Folder 4: 6-10)
  - D32. Armenian question, clippings, 1908-1921 (Folder 4: 11)
    Note
    Mainly materials related to the Russo-Turkish war.
  - D33. Cables to Rushidi Paşa, Turkish Commandant of Agaba, circa 1830 (Folder 5: 1-12)
  - D35. Tanzimat period of reformations, 1839-1876, pamphlets, newspapers, and clippings, 1863, 1904-1943 (Folder 5: 13-16)
  - D36. Ottoman Countercoup of 1909, newspapers, clippings and pamphlets, 1909-1938 (Folder 5: 17-21)
  - D37. Coat of Arms of Republic discussion, clippings, 1923-1924 (Folder 6: 1)
  - D38. Bibliography notes on the Islamic mezheps, 1924-1927 (Folder 6: 2)
  - D39. Occupation of Istanbul during truce, clippings, newspapers, pamphlets, and maps, 1919-1923 (Folder 6: 3-8)
    Includes Treaty of Peace with Turkey. Signed at Sèvres, August 10, 1920, presented to Parliament by Command of His Majesty, London, 1920
  - D41. Occupation of Izmir and Bursa during truce, newspapers, clippings, pamphlets, and notes, 1921-1922, 1938 (Folder 6: 9-13)
  - D45. "The Straits Question," notes, clippings and newspapers, 1910-1942 (Folder 7: 1-3)
  - D46. Abdülmecit devrinde, clippings, 1935-1939 (Folder 7: 4)
  - D47. Mehmed Murad V, pamphlets, clippings, and postcard, 1856-1878 (Folder 7: 5)
  - D48. First period of Parliament, newspapers and clippings, 1838-1879 (Folder 7: 6-10)
  - D49. Kuvayi Milliye, clippings, 1847 (Folder 7: 11)
  - D51. Victories during the War of Independence, clippings and pamphlets, 1919-1923 (Folder 7: 12, Folder 8: 1-4)
  - D52. Kurds, clippings, pamphlets, and notes, 1925 (Folder 8: 5-6)
  - D53. Population statistics, 1890-1917 (Folder 8: 7)
  - D54. Religious questions, clippings, 1914-1920 (Folder 8: 8)
  - D55. Treaties, pamphlets, clippings, and maps, 1836-1918 (Folder 8: 9-10)
  - D56. Absolutism period, financial documents, circa 1850 (Folder 8: 11)
  - D57. Absolutism period, books, newspapers, and clippings, 1844-1912 (Folder 8: 12-14)
  - D58. Balkan War, clippings, pamphlets, and maps, 1912-1925 (Folder 9: 1-6)
  - D60. Turkish affairs, clippings from British newspapers and scrapbook, 1875-1881 (Folder 34)
  - D62. Kurdish problems, notes, clippings, and pamphlets, 1884-1927 (Folder 9: 7-10)
  - D64. German Emperor Wilhelm II's visit to Istanbul in 1898, clippings, photographs and postcards, 1891-1941 (Folder 10: 1-4)
  - D65. Arab claims and movements, clippings and pamphlet, 1894 (Folder 10: 5)
  - D66. Zionism, Semitism, and Anti-Semitism, clippings and pamphlets, 1715-1944 (Folder 10: 6-10, Folder 11: 1-4)
  - D67. Şair Eşref writings printed in newspapers, 1906-1928 (Folder 11: 5-10)
  - D68. Ayaz Ishaki writings, 1910 (Folder 11: 11)
  - D69. Oriental question, pamphlets, notes and bibliography, 1876-1913 (Folder 11: 12, Folder 12: 1-2)
  - D70. Baha'ism, clippings, circa 1902 (Folder 12: 3)
  - D71. Russian ambassador at Constantinople Nicolas Tcharykow (Charikoff), correspondence, business cards, financial documents, appeals, statements, photographs, invitations, and clippings, 1893-1936 (Folder 12: 4-12)
  - D73. Greek Syllogus Literary Society, Constantinople, correspondence and appeals, 1903-1924 (Folder 12: 13)
  - D74. Leaders of political parties, articles from Tasiviri Efkâr, 1941-1942 (Folder 12: 14)
  - D75. Ismail Gasprinsky (Gaspirali), clippings, pamphlet, and post card, 1881-1918 (Folder 13: 1)
  - D79. Ahmed Midhat (Mithat Paşa), articles, clippings, pamphlets, obituaries, and bibliographical notes, 1870-1949 (Folder 13: 2-11)
  - D80. Vilayet of Eastern Rumelia, pamphlets, 1880 (Folder 13: 12-13)
  - D81. Second Constitution, clippings, pamphlets, and newspapers, 1908-1930 (Folder 13: 14-15, Folder 14: 1)
  - D82. and D86. Ittihad ve Terakki (Committee of Union and Progress), clippings and pamphlets, 1916 (Folder 14: 2-3)
  - D83. Serbest Cumhuriyet Firkasi (Free Republican Party), clippings, 1927-1930 (Folder 14: 4)
  - D84. Hürriyet ve Itilâf Firkasi (Party of Freedom and Accord), pamphlets and clippings, 1910-1943 (Folder 14: 5)
  - D91. Hürriyet ve Itilâf Firkasi Sadik Bey leader, clippings, 1941 (Folder 14: 6)
  - D96. Turkish Jews during foreign occupation, clippings, 1943 (Folder 14: 7)
    Includes receipts from a telegraph company, 1922
  - D97. Reyam-I Sabah, Anatolia, 1921 (Folder 14: 8)
  - D100. Yenigün, Ankara, 1920 (Folder 14: 9-10)
  - D102. Statures of some societies and companies, circa 1850 (Folder 14: 11)
  - D105. Mustafa Kemal Atatürk's memoirs and clippings, 1926-1938 (Folder 14: 12-14, Folder 15: 1-3)
  - D106. War of Independence, clippings, 1922 (Folder 15: 4)
  - D107. Highest Russian Commercial Committee for Near East (Vysshyi torgovyi komitet dlia Blizhnego Vostoka), minutes, correspondence, and reports, 1919 April-November (Folder 15: 5-7)
  - D109. "Correspondance concernant l'introduction des réformes dans les provinces arméniennes de la Turquie d'Asie,", 1984-1896 (Folder 15: 8-9)
  - D111. Ittihad-i Islâm, clippings, circa 1905 (Folder 15: 10)
  - D115. Cemal Paşa, clippings and correspondence, 1919-1943 (Folder 15: 11)
  - D118. Russian ambassador at Constantinople Nicolas Charikoff (Tcharykow), correspondence, business cards, photonegatives, financial documents, appeals, statements, and clippings, 1887-1938 (Folder 15: 12-16, Folder 16: 1-7)
  - D119. Kâzim Karabekir Paşa, clippings, 1924-1939 (Folder 16: 8-11)
  - D120. Printing shops regulations, 1884-1918 (Folder 16: 12)
  - D124. Mustafa İsmet İnönü, newspapers, clippings, and pamphlets, 1935-1943 (Folder 16: 13-16)
  - D128. Ahmet Hikmet Müftüoğlu, clippings, 1918 (Folder 17: 1)
  - D129. Rumbeyoğlu Fahrettin's foreign affairs, clippings, 1918 (Folder 17: 2)
  - D131. Emre Ahmed Cerad's political writings, clippings, 1920 (Folder 17: 3)
  - D133. Sultan Abdülhamid II's real estate documents, circa 1900 (Folder 17: 4-5)
  - D134. Abdul Medjid Effendi elected Caliph, clippings and pamphlets, 1921-1922 (Folder 17: 6-7)
  - D135. Sultan Abdülhamid II, clippings, pamphlets, and notes, 1892-1945 (Folder 17: 8-12)
  - D140. D142. Armenian question, clippings, pamphlets, letters, and reports, 1797-1925 (Folder 18: 1-4)
  - D141. Yusuf Ziya and Mehmet Fuat Köprülü dispute, clippings, 1927 (Folder 18: 5-7)
  - DE1. La dette publique, Banque Ottomane, Patriarchats, financial documents and clippings, 1905-1943 (Folder 18: 8-10)
  - DE2. Prince Sabahattin, centralism and decentralism, clippings and pamphlets, 1907-1941 (Folder 18: 11-12)
  - DE3. Jihad during World War I, fatwas (statements on legal points) and clippings, 1914-1917 (Folder 19: 1-2)
  - DE4. Rapport du Dr. Israël Aurbach Délégué de la Grande Loge No XI aux lieux du désastre causé par le tremblement de terre du 9 Août 1912 (Folder 19: 3)
  - DE5. Sheikhs, correspondence among their murids, circa 1875 (Folder 19: 4)
  - DE8 and DE 22. Freemasonry, articles, clippings, and notes, 1911-1937 (Folder 19: 5-6)
  - DE9. Instruction sent to officials in provinces, 1859 (Folder 19: 7)
  - DE11. Religious instructions, notes, clippings and pamphlets, 1917 (Folder 19: 8)
  - DE12. Sivas Normal School, brochure, published by the school, Turkey, 1906 (Folder 19: 9)
  - DE15. Court eunuchs, clippings, 1908 (Folder 19: 10)
  - DE17. First laws, pamphlet, 1870 (Folder 19: 11)
  - DE19. Artisan's concessions, pamphlets, cuttings, and notes, 1913-1942 (Folder 19: 12)
  - DE20. Muslim monasteries, clippings, 1810 (Folder 19: 13)
  - DE21. The Hague Convention of 1899, clippings and pamphlet, 1899-1911 (Folder 19: 14)
  - DE25. Family law, pamphlets and clippings, 1911-1939 (Folder 19: 15)
  - DE28. Foreign occupation of Istanbul, notes, clippings and postcards, 1918 (Folder 19: 16)
  - DE31. Medrese reforms, clippings, pamphlets, and notes, 1910- 1916 (Folder 20: 1-3)
  - DE34. Marriage, divorce, and private international law documents, 1900-1938 (Folder 20: 4-7)
    Includes correspondence and clippings
  - DE36. Slavery history, writings, circa 1800 (Folder 20: 8)
  - DE38. Army organization, pictures, clippings, and pamphlets, 1900-1914 (Folder 20: 9-11)
  - DE40. Industrial schools, pamphlets and clippings, 1920-1923 (Folder 20: 12-13)
  - DE34. Marriage, divorce, and private international law documents, 1900-1938 (Folder 20: 4-7)
    Include correspondence and clippings,
  - DE36. Slavery history, writings, circa 1800 (Folder 20: 8)
  - DE38. Army organization, pictures, clippings, and pamphlets, 1900-1914 (Folder 20: 9-11)
  - DE40. Industrial schools, pamphlets and clippings, 1920-1923 (Folder 20: 12-13)
  - DE41. Schools in old times, clippings, circa 1925 (Folder 20: 14)
  - DE42. Religious court regulations, clippings and pamphlet, 1914-1924 (Folder 20: 15)
  - DE43. Nâzim Hikmet, clippings, 1922 (Folder 20: 16)
  - DE44. Mekteb-i Mülkiye-school for civil servants, history, regulations, and program, 1918-1934 (Folder 21: 1)
  - DE45. Communism in Turkey, clippings, 1917-1929 (Folder 21: 2-15)
  - DE46. Ottoman capitulations, clippings and pamphlets, 1895-1923 (Folder 21: 16-17)
- Research folios, 1800-1955 (Box 22-24)
  The dossiers contain oversize materials from the larger group of research files selected by collector, originally designated as "binders" in incomplete series AI.1-4b, AII.1-4, BI.1-2b, CI.1a-7, CII.1-9, and CIII. Materials have been rehoused into oversize files for preservation purposes.
  - AI.1-2, 1800-1920
    - Fatwa against the nationalist movement in Asia Minor, April 1920 (Folder 22: 1)
    - Tax forms, 1841 (Folder 22: 2)
    - Abdul Aziz decree to Sadrazam Mehmet Emin Paşa, 1861 (Folder 22: 3)
    - Mustafa Fazil Paşa letter to Sultan Abdul-Aziz regarding abuses arising from absolute rule and the advantages to be derived from constitutional government, circa 1860 (Folder 22: 4)
    - Samples of Resit Paşa's letterheads, 1829 (Folder 22: 5)
    - Rumelian siyahetnameh of Abdulmecid, 1846 (Folder 22: 6)
    - Resit Paşa's writings relating to the Russo-Turkish War, 1853 (Folder 22: 7)
    - Khulasat al-burhan fi ita'at al-sultan, by Seykülislam Yastaci zadeh Abdulwahhab, 1831 (Folder 22: 8)
    - Suleyman Paşa's draft for reforms in Rumelia, 1909 (Folder 22: 9)
    - Kitab fi 'ilm al-kalam, by Ibn al-Qadi al-Daghistani, circa 1800 (Folder 22: 10)
  - AI.3-5, 1845-1919
    - First Constitutional Period, pamphlets, clippings and correspondence, 1845-1906 (Folder 22: 11-15)
    - Second Constitutional Period, correspondence, clippings, military orders, legal documents, proclamations, maps, and postcards, 1859-1919 (Folder 22: 16-28)
  - BI, 1919-1923
    - Patriotic song of Izmir, 1922 (Folder 22: 29)
    - Musalimet-i cihan, by Meliha Naci, 1922 (Folder 22: 30)
    - Program of celebration of the Army's victory, Ankara, 1922 (Folder 22: 31)
    - Defense of Rights Committee of Samsun proclamation to the Türkiye Büyük Millet Meclisi (TBMM) and to the people of Ankara on the War with Greece, 25 August 1922 (Folder 22: 32)
    - Anadolu ajansi, bulletin, 1920 (Folder 22: 33)
    - Sadrazam Tevfik Pasa note to the TBMM on the Peace Conference, 29 October 1922 (Folder 22: 34)
    - Proclamation on volunteers recruitment for the 5th Army Corps, 1919 (Folder 22: 35)
    - Istiklal Mahkemesi and the Taal-i Islam Cemiyeti circulars, 1919-1920 (Folder 22: 36)
    - Mustafa Kemal Atatürk proclamation on allied occupation of Istanbul, 16 March 1920 (Folder 22: 37)
    - Certain deputies proposal to separate the Caliphate from the Sultanate, 1922 (Folder 22: 38)
    - Misak-i Iktisâdi drawn up at the Economic Congress of Smyrna, 1923 (Folder 22: 39)
    - Türk bugünkü vazifesi, booklet, circa 1919 (Folder 22: 40)
    - Western Thrace Society proclamation, 1922 (Folder 22: 41)
    - Period of defense of rights, 1919-1920 (Folder 22: 42)
  - BII. Republic of Turkey file, notes, correspondence, and pamphlet, 1905-1926 (Folder 23: 1-2)
    Includes photographs related to Kara Kemal suicide, 1926
  - CI, 1859-1956
    - Fatwas on marriage, 1901 (Folder 23: 3)
    - Marriage permits, 1859-1918 (Folder 23: 4-8)
    - Divorce certificates, 1892-1909 (Folder 23: 9)
    - Arşiv Bülteni Nos. 1-2, Türk Devrim Tarihi Enstitüsü, 1944-1945 (Folder 23: 10)
    - Kerim Kâmi Key writings, Washington, D.C., 1952-1955 (Folder 23: 11)
    - Trakya-Paï¿½aeli Müdafaa-i Hukuk Cemiyeti'nin, minutes, 9 May 1920 (Folder 23: 12-14)
    - Askeri Okullarımız Tanıyalım writings and clippings, 1955-1956 (Folder 23: 15)
    - Hasan-ï¿½li Yücel writings and clippings, 1952-1955 (Folder 23: 16, Folder 24: 1-5)
    - Londra Konferansı, clippings, 1921 (Folder 24: 6)
    - Miscellany newspapers and clippings, 1899-1921 (Folder 24: 7-11)
- Large research dossiers, 1818-1951 (Box 25-29)
  - AI.1-3, 1833-1910
    - Varaka-i-Mashsusa, special dispatch sent to Istanbul by the High Command on the Turkish victory over the Russians at Ruscak, 1854 (1270) (Folder 25)
    - Ottoman costumes illustrations on postcards sent to Constantin Plessos, Cadikeny, 1908-1909 (Folder 25)
    - Takvim-i vekai, articles on internal affairs, 1833-1846 (1249-1262) (Folder 25)
    - Orman nizarmamesi (Forestry regulations), 1870 (1286) (Folder 25)
    - First firmans of Tanzimat period, circa 1850 (Folder 25)
    - The First Constitution, manuscript, 1877 (1293) (Folder 25)
    - Directives to governors, mustasarrifs, qaimaqams and mudurs, 1859 (1275) (Folder 25)
    - Expense account regulations for military officers when on tour, 1845 (1261) (Folder 25)
    - Basiret, journal, 1286 (1870) (Folder 25)
    - The Arabian Peninsula and Rumelia list of taxes levied, 1267 (1851) (Folder 25)
    - Ali and Fuad Paşas Vasiyetnameh, pt. II, Tarih-i Osmani Anjuman-I Mecmuasi, Haziran, 1326 (1910) (Folder 25)
    - Melkon Han deportation, and its repercussion in Turk-Iranian relations, letter, 1279 (1863) (Folder 25)
    - Qu'il soit fait en conformité du contenu, imprimerie de la Presse d'Orient, 1856 (Folder 25)
    - Penal Law, 1254-1256 (1838-1840) (Folder 25)
  - AI.4a, 1882-1918
    - Decree relating to the title of Marshal to be conferred on the Austrian-Hungarian Emperor, clippings, 19 May 1918 (Folder 25)
    - Notre Bien Aimé Souverain Sultan Abdoul Hamid Han II picture, circa 1322 (1906) (Folder 25)
    - Ruling of contributions for military purposes, 1896 (Folder 25)
    - İbrahim Edhem Paşa picture, circa 1850 (Folder 25)
    - Abraham Paşa forest and farms value, report, 1305 (1887) (Folder 25)
    - Informers report on a soldier Ali, who was in the habit of collecting forbidden newspapers entering the country through the Austrian Post Office, 1313 (1897) (Folder 25)
    - Sadrazam Rifat Paşa letter relating to the decoration which was to be conferred on the Beys Adil and Fuat, February 1316 (1900) (Folder 25)
    - Abdülhamid II urine analysis laboratory report, 1322 (1906) (Folder 25)
    - Seyh ul-Islam report to Abdülhamid II relating to incidents arising among students of the Süleymaniyye Medresesi, circa 1890 (Folder 25)
    - Mighat Paşa speech delivered after his condemnation to death, circa 1882 (Folder 25)
  - A.I.4b, 1888-1924
    - Diploma conferring decoration on Ali Riza Paşa with Wilhelm signature, 1898 (Folder 25)
    - Security secretary letter requesting the Sultan for an increase in salary, 28 May 1308 (1892) (Folder 25)
    - Zabtiyye Naziri letter relating to the nomination of Ahmet Raghib to the Presidency of a commission of inquiry, 1315 (1899) (Folder 25)
    - Zabtiyye Naziri proposal to the Sultan to raise the salary of an official, 1308 (1892) (Folder 25)
    - Zabtiyye Naziri letter to the Sultan requesting salary increases for certain officials, 1304 and 1321 (1888 and 1902) (Folder 25)
    - List of persons condemned to death or banishment, circa 1317 (1901) (Folder 25)
    - Popular song on the war between Turkey and Greece, circa 1892 (Folder 25)
    - Ikdam preserved for article on barracks of Tas Kislar, copy, 10 June 1924 (Folder 25)
    - "Turkey Limited," cartoon against Abdülhamid, 1896 (Folder 25)
    - Salnameh-i Askeri first page dedicated to Abdülhamid, circa 1890 (Folder 25)
    - Malumat, the various appointments made to official positions by Abdülhamid, Muharram 1319 (1903) (Folder 25)
    - "Abdülhamid destani," by Yusuf Niyazi, satirical poem against AbdAbdülhamid destanilhamid, circa 1320 (1904) (Folder 25)
    - Baskumandan Riza Paşa regulations to military service, 1311 (1895) (Folder 25)
    - An army officer report to the Sultan Baskatib condemning the maladministration of Omer Lufti Paşa in Salonika, 1903 (Folder 25)
  - A.II.1, 1880-1917
    - Tughra, circa 1909 (Folder 26)
    - Ministry of Education circular announcing that the title of Ghazi has been conferred on Mehmet V for the victory over the allies at the Dardanelles, 15 April 1333 (1917) (Folder 26)
    - The decree of Abdühamid to Prime Minister Said Paşa, announcements in Gazetta, 20 July 1324 (1908) (Folder 26)
      Includes Terekki Mektebi ve Gazetesi, circa 1890
    - Troops from Rumelia, pictures, circa 1880 (Folder 26)
    - Les Sauveurs de la Constitution Turque, poster, circa 1900 (Folder 26)
    - Trabzon, 7 March 1332 (1917) (Folder 26)
    - Papaghan, special colored editions, 10 July 1908 and 17 December 1908 (Folder 26)
    - Mehmet V to Meclis-i Mebusan, inaugural speech, 1909 (Folder 26)
  - A.II.2, 1908-1910
    - Mimeographed invitation by the Sadrazam on the occasion of the Mevlud 11 Rabi ul-ovvel, 1326 (1910) (Folder 26)
    - Proposed changes to certain articles of the Constitution, Meclis-i Mobusan, No. 26, Birinci Devre, 1324-1325 (1908-1909) (Folder 26)
    - Fatwa deposing Abdülhamid, Sabah, 17 April 1909 (Folder 26)
    - The commander of the Third Army, proclamations and declaration of martial law, Servet-i Funun, 12 April 1325 (1909) (Folder 26)
    - The change of the Sultanate, Sabah, 14 April 1325 (1909) (Folder 26)
    - Sultan Mehmet V pictures, circa 1909 (Folder 26)